Diana Villasana Ocampo

ACTUARIAL SCIENCE | STATITICS

Mexico City, Mexico

▼ dvillasanao@hotmail.com | ☑ dvillasanao | ऻ dvillasanao | У dvillasanao

SUMMARY

Statistician specialist with skills and experience in demographic planning for the development of public policies at the national level. Among the activities conducted on a daily are the provision of specialized technical advice to different federal and local public administration agencies; as well as the updating and management of surveys, censuses, and vital statistics for the generation of socio-demographic diagnoses and research topics.

EDUCATION

Applied Statistics

ANAHUAC UNIVERSITY

Actuarial Science

ANAHUAC UNIVERSITY

Evaluation of the Public Policies and Programs

UED - SECRETARIAT OF FINANCE AND PUBLIC CREDIT (SHCP)

Master degree

2018 - 2020

Bachelor degree

2010 - 2015

Diploma Course Sepetember 2023

WORK HISTORY

Head of Internal Migration Department

NATIONAL POPULATION COUNCIL (CONAPO)

Mexico City, Mexico

2017 - Present

- Developed and executed research projects on marginalization, poverty, vulnerability, internal migration, general mobility, internal displacement, and related socio-demographic indicators to inform demographic planning in the country, resulting in evidence-based policy recommendations and interventions.
- Researched and analyzed population and development data from diverse sources, resulting in the creation of comprehensive technical responses utilized by federal public administration agencies to inform decision-making and policy development, driving effective resource allocation, and promoting sustainable development outcomes.

Achivements

RURAL FINANCIAL

- Methodological improvements in the scheme of the Marginalization Index in all the different levels of geographical disaggregation are key to the social policies and government programs of the country
- Evaluate the quality of the environment in issues of equipment for the Official Mexican Standards for Certification of Disability (PROY-NOM-039-SSA-2023).
- Implementation of the Odisea | Mexico platform in collaboration with the United Nations Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean (ECLAC) of the Population Division of CELADE. (Link: https://odisea.redatam.org/mex/).

Assistant in the Internal Migration Department

Mexico City, Mexico

NATIONAL POPULATION COUNCIL (CONAPO)

January 2016 - July 2016

- Conducted research on internal migration laws and policies to ensure compliance and accuracy.
- Database management and analysis on migration, marginalization, and socio-demographic indicators.

Coordination assistant of Risk Department

Mexico City, Mexico

January 2010 - November

• Provided administrative support to the coordination team, including document preparation, data entry, and file man-

• Assisted in coordinating and monitoring risk management activities to ensure compliance with company policies.

Hard Skills

- Sampling and Census
- Survey
- Data Mining
- Machine Learning
- Data Visualization
- Public Policy
- Policy Evaluation

Software Skills

Advanced

- R
- Python
- SPSS Statistics

Software Skills

Intermediate

- SAS
- STATA
- ArcGIS
- SQL
- PowerBI | DAX
- Visual Studio Code

Programming language

- HTML
- CSS
- LaTeX

Soft Skills

- Project Management
- Verbal and Writting Communication
- Public Communication

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. CONAPO. (2023). Environment quality index 2020. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2023*. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/856497/LSDM23_Completo.pdf
- 2. CONAPO. (2023). Conceptual and methodological changes of marginalization indices 2020. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2022*. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/783840/SDM_Parte9.pdf.
- 3. CONAPO. (2022). Diagnosis on the situation of internal forced displacement in mexico. Internal Forced Displacement in Mexico: From the Recognition of Challenges, 25 35. http://www.derechoshumanos.gob.mx/work/models/Derechos_Humanos/DGPPDH/pdf/DESPLAZAMIENTO_FORZADO_INTERNO_EN_MEXICO.pdf
- 4. CONAPO. (2022). National diagnosis about internal forced displacement in mexico. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/diagnostico-nacional-sobre-la-sitacion-del-desplazamiento-forzado-interno-en-mexico
- 5. CONAPO. (2022). Recent internal return migration in mexico. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico* 2021, 125 147. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/la-situacion-demografica-de-mexico-2021
- 6. CONAPO. (2021). Index of marginalization by locality 2020. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-de-marginacion-2020-284372
- 7. CONAPO. (2021). Index of marginalization by AGEB 2020. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-de-marginacion-2020-284372
- 8. CONAPO. (2021). Index of marginalization by state and municipality 2020. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/indices-de-marginacion-2020-284372
- 9. CONAPO. (2019). The equipment in the urbanized areas of mexico, 2018. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2019*, 109 131. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/la-situacion-demografica-de-mexico-2019

- 10. CONAPO. (2019). Sociodemographic profile of the population that changed their home or place of residence to protect themselves from crime. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/514162/PERFIL_SOCIODEMOGRAFICO_final_ISBN.pdf.
- 11. CONAPO. (2019). Student mobility in mexico. *The Demographic Situation of Mexico 2018*, 124 141. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/491898/p124-p141.pdf.
- 12. CONAPO, & UNFPA. (2019). Violence as a cause of forced internal displacement, approaches to its analysis in mexico. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/es/documentos/la-violencia-como-causa-de-desplazamiento-interno-forzado-aproximaciones-a-su-analisis-e state=published
- 13. SEDATU, & CONAPO. (2018). National urban system 2018. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/sistema-urbano-nacional-2018
- 14. CONPO. (2016). Marginalization index by state and municipality 2015. https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/459282/00_Preliminares.pdf.
- 15. SEDATU, CONAPO, & INEGI. (2016). Delimitation of the metropolitan areas of mexico 2015. https://www.gob.mx/conapo/documentos/delimitacion-de-las-zonas-metropolitanas-de-mexico-2015